<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Product Teams | Academic</title><link>https://dimkastan.github.io/category/product-teams/</link><atom:link href="https://dimkastan.github.io/category/product-teams/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Product Teams</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://dimkastan.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Product Teams</title><link>https://dimkastan.github.io/category/product-teams/</link></image><item><title>Endless development cycles with Agile and how to avoid them</title><link>https://dimkastan.github.io/post/endless-development-cycle-in-agile-teams/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dimkastan.github.io/post/endless-development-cycle-in-agile-teams/</guid><description>&lt;!-- ```python
import libr
print('hello')
-->
&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Some agile teams are facing an endless development cycle. This is caused mainly by two types of stakeholders and customers. Those who are sticked to traditional waterfall methods or by those that misinterpret the agile approach in a way that they try to use it as a vehicle for continuous new product development. This article presents this commonly faced problems and some health check and suggestions to help teams for teams early detect them&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="problem-description">Problem description&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>While Agile provides an iterative approach for project management, promoting change, collaboration, adaptive planning, and flexibility in responses, often it is misused as a non-ending sprint loop. In principle agile methodologies like Scrum, clearly define that at every sprint, the team is building a potentially releasable increment. In this manner, the team, while in a short term, is delivering value to the customer. However, many stakeholders or customers that are sticked to the traditional project management, fail to actively participate in this iterative development approach.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="symptoms">Symptoms&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Here are two main symptoms that are usually noticed across agile teams.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Stakeholders waiting for something “complete” at every sprint to move on.
It has to be very clear that this will never happen. Each sprint ensures that a small increment is built- and potentially released. Even if that happens, that means that either the product was too simple, or that something is really missing. Here is crucial to elicitate feedback from the stakeholders and feedback from actual releases.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Stakeholders never stop asking for improvements and introduce new features/products
There is also the trap of continuously asking for new features or even changing the specification. While this is normal as new features naturally arise in agile development, the team has to acknowledge that new features should arise if and only if they are mandatory in order to address the defined objective. Otherwise, customers/stakeholders will always raise the bar by hiding behind the “deliver value to the customer” excuse.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="proposed-actions">Proposed actions&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Agile, and in particular Scrum is based on the pillars of Transparency, Inspection and Adaptation. If followed thoroughly all parties will benefit by the flexibility provided by the framework. Here are some recommendations/ health-checks for teams following the Agile development methodology&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Make sure that your increments reach the real customers&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Don’t delay releases if and only if the concern is expressed by some stackeholders, team members&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If someone is causing the team to procrastinate the release try to understand what are his/hers concerns&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Agile applies for the whole product. If one (sub) team is using different approach make sure this is not intervening to the agile process&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Don’t judge agile development cycles with a traditional project management perspective&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Discovery is part of progress.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If the team is not delivering something useful, try to communicate that in the review&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ask the team if the increment is providing new features o&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Check the acceptance criteria- if need to update to maximize value make sure that this is not by adding a new feature&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Hope this will help you in your agile journey!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Brain inspired business organization structure and operations</title><link>https://dimkastan.github.io/post/brain-inspired-business-organization/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dimkastan.github.io/post/brain-inspired-business-organization/</guid><description>&lt;!-- ```python
import libr
print('hello')
``` -->
&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Scientists are known for their ability of transfering concepts from one domain to another. This phenomenon follows the principle that nature is built on some very common princinples. Additionally, as human beings we tend to immitate nature- including biological organisms. For example, aeronautical engineers used concepts observed in bird spiecies to design aircrafts. Machine learning engineers are inspired by human brains and their ability to learn from examples. This article provides a brain inspired business organization and operation analogy, hoping that will help teams understand some fundamental concepts immanent to a organ that is designed to learn, develop, adapt, act, visualize and imagine! &lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="brain-inspired-business-organization-structure-and-operations">Brain inspired business organization structure and operations&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Human brain is a complex organ responsible for coordinating our body functions and maintaining a status of the self amongst other tasks. During the wake state, our brain perceives information from the environment and creates representations of the word, develops new skills that are vital for our surviving and important for every interaction with the outer world. Neuroscientists are constantly unfolding the knowledge around brain functionality which despite important for the neuroscience field is didactic and source of inspiration for other scientific fields. A characteristic example is the area of Machine Learning where a system tries to imitate the ability of a human brain to learn feature feature mappings between domains given some examples- usually accompanied with a supervisory signals. In the early days Sparse Representations were imitating the ability of the visual cortex to encode visual information while more recently, deep learning methods try to replicate brain’s ability to build hierarchical representations in a simplified digital model.
In this article, I am presenting the organization structure of a business from a brain inspired perspective. Human brains evolve, visualize, learn, create structures, create data processing channels, store information while they try to reduce the energy consumption by optimizing structures that support common activities. Similarly, a business is evolving, learns how to adapt to the market, creates structures, dedicated units to perform specific actions, automates processes and changes it’s structure over time. It is therefore obvious that a business can benefit by understanding or relating its substance with that of a human brain.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="analogy">Analogy&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Human brains receive information from various sensors. These sensors are naturally limited to gather specific information and the brain creates meaningful representations under several objectives. For a specific period, the human brain matures, creating more complex structures reaching at a plateau at some point. Then, these structures are optimized to minimize energy consumption, however the journey does not stop there. New memories come over, new skills are developed and different parts of the brain can start contributing in different tasks over time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In a similar manner a businesses mature, develop new skills, create a representation of the world- as it is perceived- and change their structure. Businesses, collect information and make steps based on an internal representation of the actual world (e.g. market).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From a brain inspired business organization analogy, it is evident that:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>As long as the business grow, its structure will be subject to change&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A business organizationsneeds to optimize and create strong connections&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Parts of a business might need to change roles/functions&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Learning new skills is mandatory&lt;/li>
&lt;li>business organizations sense only what they observe Be aware that there is always missing information&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="be-aware-of-the-level-of-detail-needed">Be aware of the level of detail needed&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>It is very common for people to believe that they observe their world around them in great detail. Scientific experiments have shown however, that the humans see in a very abstract manner. To understand that try to sketch a one dollar or euro. This is a great example showcasing that the level of detail needed to perform a task is not always very fine-grained.
Businesses organizations need to provide the least amount of details in order to avoid an overflow of information which might hide what’s important or affect information from other topics to be observed.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="organization-plasticity-and-catastrophic-forgeting">Organization Plasticity and catastrophic forgeting&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Businesse organizations should be agile and flexible in order to survive. Of vital importance is to have departments that can gradually shift to a different specialization by learning/developing new skills. In this manner, existing resources are reused and further benefit by transferring concepts from different areas of expertise.
Also be aware that once new tasks are learnt, old will gradually fade out in favor of new skills and memories. Therefore, organization plasticity should be strategically orchestrated.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="on-making-decisions--while-avoiding-illusions">On making decisions- while avoiding illusions&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Humans make decisions every in instance. They control they body, validate they optical, acoustic and other senses, predict, act and repeat. However, sometimes, humans are not seeing or not hearing. Additionally, it can be the case that the visual and the acoustic signals disagree or that the signals are limited to actually observe what is happening.
Magicians are aware of these shortcomings to entertain people with tricks and illusions. For a business however, it is important to take decisions while minimizing wrong or misleading interpretations. Fusing information, or validating, from multiple sources can help on that (e.g. didn’t see it but I heard it). Additionally, in case of brain damage, wrong signals arrive or signals are not reaching the target. Business should develop the tools to detect these “damages” by running some diagnostics.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Epilogue and suggestions&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Nature always inspires us. In science it is very common to transfer concepts from one domain to another and in this manner, we can always find analogies. Analogies will help us to dive deeper to the notion and will ignite our imagination.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Below you can find some suggestions that you can apply at your organization.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Business organizations need to decide how they will create a representation of the market (outer world). This can include market, the technology, the economy and other trends,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Use all possible ways to interact with the market. Different departments like sales, growth, engineer, finance working in parallel can give a better understanding of what is really happening&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A company needs different operational modes. Some things need to run fast, without a lot of thinking, while others slow, engaging more ‘units’ and effort. The fast and slow modes can make big difference so an organization needs to determine the modes/follow a process&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Organizations are limited in terms of sensing and capacity. To get the most of an organization, it’s structure needs to be optimized and the people within should have strong communication channels&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Complex tasks need multiple departments/units to collaborate. The more often you do that the more efficient it will be (e.g. hand-eye coordination)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Organization should invest in specialization of repetitive functionalities and long term functionalities&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Pursue detail when really needed. Always ask this within your team: How does knowing more details about A will help me solve B? In machine learning there is the notion of early stop.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When to change? If you get a signal that resources are spent without results that means that you need another structure, not more resources!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Search for meaning! This will fuel the teams within organization maintain their activity and pace!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Realize that most information is not observable.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Understand an map the operations within an organization.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>How long does it take to have a signal received from sensor 1 (e.g. customer feedback) until it reaches the product manager and then how follow up actions reach the engineering team or upper management?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Flattening the structure/communication channels can improve the latency but it has to be ensured that only the signals reach to the right destination&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Hope that this will help you better think of your business organization!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Let's build things right (this time) mindset- Does it help at all</title><link>https://dimkastan.github.io/post/historic-recurrence-in-tech-teams/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dimkastan.github.io/post/historic-recurrence-in-tech-teams/</guid><description>&lt;!-- ```python
import libr
print('hello')
``` -->
&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;em>A common belief in (tech) teams working on wicked problems is that they start the project with some wrong choices or missing information. Whilst this is very common in complext problems, teams always tend to &amp;lsquo;blame&amp;rsquo; the first steps of the project as opposed to searching for adaptation.When teams stick on this mindset, they tend to repeat the same mistakes over and over again and when they retrospect the see only the mistakes or wrong choices made in the beggining and overlook the importance to learn and adapt. This article, presents this mindset as a historical recurrence trap and suggests some methods that will (hopefully) help teams spot and escape from it.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="introduction">introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Mark Twain once said, “History never repeats itself, but it does often rhyme”. In school we were taught that people should learn from history, meaning that humans need to learn from past mistakes. However, people really struggle to follow this rule of thumb- and there is a reason for that. Indeed, apart from politics and sociology, people face the same challenge in everyday lives meaning, family, work and personal relationships. In this short article, I will focus on the “Historic recurrence” effect in technological teams.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="i-classfa-fa-rocket-fa-appear-fa-1x-stylecolor-grayi-problem-description">&lt;i class="fa fa-rocket fa-appear fa-1x" style="color: gray">&lt;/i> Problem description&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A new project is about to commence and depending of the selected way-of-work the team is somehow structured. While discussing the what, the how and the when, one of the most used phrases noticed amongst peers is, namely, the “let’s build it right this time” or “let’s organize it better”, “let’s sell it better”, “let’s design it better“, following the “Let’s &lt;verb> it better” structure. Ideally, it should stop there, the statement should be followed by the “do it right” solution and the project should run within budget, time and scope leaving the end user/customer satisfied. However, it seems that this phrase is quite vague depicting lack of structure, processes, or even experience. Let’s dig a little bit into this phrase.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="i-classfa-fa-magnifying-glass-stylecolor-grayi-analysis">&lt;i class="fa fa-magnifying-glass" style="color: gray">&lt;/i> Analysis&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This statement should not be underestimated. It is a strong indicator that some team members were not satisfied by the way they worked in the past or the result of their work. What is difficult to understand is that this can vary across team members according to their objectives. For example, business people try to optimize the outcome within the given budget. Project managers try to control the budget, scope and time while development teams try to generate as much value as possible for the customer with the minimal possible technical debt. These teams need to find a balance and it is not guaranteed at all that all of them will be satisfied at the same time.
For business people, this statement could refer to their disappointment regarding budget and revenue. Project managers could use it to highlight to the team the importance of providing more “accurate” estimations. Finally the development teams could refer to the technical debt as well as prolonged latencies in getting feedback from the customers.
However, teams should comprehend that they are trying to jointly optimize different objectives. This is very common in Machine learning tasks formulated as multi-task and/or multi-objective problems or constraint optimization problems, where an objective is optimized subject to several predefined criteria. As Machine Learning teaches us, we are always responsible for what we choose to optimize against as well as how we evaluate out results and the tradeoffs within. For example, you might have the right objective but the training data might not be representative of the problem or we might be interested in reducing False Positives in favor of increasing the False Negative Rate.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="i-classfa-fa-gears-fa-spin-fa-1x-stylecolor-grayi--what-you-can-do">&lt;i class="fa fa-gears fa-spin fa-1x" style="color: gray">&lt;/i> What you can do?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Here are some suggestions to help your team be better prepared and well-structured next time:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Unlearn&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Within complex projects/products it very common that more is unknown than known. Agile methodologies cope with complexity by iteratively working on solving the problem by taking one small step at a time and checking both the output and when to go next (review) as well as the way teams, that adopt them, work (retrospective). In this manner, it often takes a team to unlearn in order to drop the tools used to work until now and build new strategies.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Avoid the mount stupid&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The well known Dunning-Kruger effect tells us that oftenly people tend to overestimate their abilities leading to poor decisions and those decisions are later transformed into project failures, technical debt and/or customer dissatisfaction.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Engage people with range&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Todays wicked problems require generalists. While specialists in a team can do the job optimally, generalists can also help to do the right job.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Hear all the voices: Imposter syndrome&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>After working for many years, you realize that things you do actually work and that your ideas are usually applicable. Lot’s of people however, believe that this is due to luck and they keep believing that they do not hold any expertise amongst their peers. In a similar manner, some juniors might have a good idea or a proposal on how to implement an idea, but they may hold back thinking that they have to wait until they “grow up”. This is known as the imposter syndrome, so a team needs to learn to also take onto account people that are not always heard in a discussion.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Define goals and objectives.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This can include the vision and key deliverables but it can go beyond that. A goal-condition formulation can be used in deliverables where the acceptance criteria should be clearly defined. Therefore, acceptance criteria describe the sweet spot between the business, the project and the development teams facilitating early estimations and fruitful discussions.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Define and revisit priorities&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>As Heraclitus said “The only constant is change”, and during a project lifecycle, priorities are no exception. Clearly communicating the effects of these changes alongside with the strategy will help the teams to align to a common goal.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Decide what to measure&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>A team has the ability to measure anything is considered valuable to them, not only in the current project but also in future ones. For example a development team can measure the technical debt, the project management can measure the planned value.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Ask team members to propose new methods&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Typically, this should take place in retrospectives. For scrum teams this can happen even in a weekly basis and it can be embedded in the Definition of Done.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Processes&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>If there is a flaw in a process make an attempt to fix it. Keep notes each time an issue raises during the project’s lifecycle and try to find a way to fix it within processes. The most important issues with the highest frequency of appearance can be prioritized.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Select a framework that will guide you&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Project Management techniques will help your team to navigate through the various tasks they need to implement while keeping their effectiveness. Those techniques will also help in coordinating, recording and evaluating project activities minimizing that way the chance of a derailed roadmap.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="epilogue">Epilogue&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>As history teaches us, even with past experiences and large amounts of data, it is not always easy to make wise decisions. Whilst most of the times relying on data and being flexible to adjust as you learn more will help you and your team to succeed, the complexity and the uncertainty can still affect your decisions and therefore your results. In case something like happen, you should try to learn as much as possible from this new experience and generate as much data as possible for the next time you will face a similar challenge. This will ultimately change the “let’s build things right this time” to “are we going to achieve the required goal with the current choices we make? ”&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hope this helps!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>To succeed you need to speak truth to power, take decisions and focus</title><link>https://dimkastan.github.io/post/to-succeed-you-need-to-speak-truth-to-power-take-decisions-and-focus/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dimkastan.github.io/post/to-succeed-you-need-to-speak-truth-to-power-take-decisions-and-focus/</guid><description>&lt;!-- ```python
import libr
print('hello')
``` -->
&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;em>What is the origin of success in businesses and in everyday lives? What are the driving forces needed to reach growth and maturity? Also, what it takes to have satisfied employees, customers and smooth transition? You often hear that this business succeeded because someone had the skills to affect the decisions or change the mind of the C-level executives. However, this is not a one mans show, and definitely not a single skill or something that takes place one time in one location.
It seems that a business needs truth to be spoken to power, ability to focus and taking decisions without procrastinating. In this article, I am tackling these factors in an attempt to highlight their effect in an organization as well as the benefits. Also, as it be made clear later, these three aspects are connected to each other in a sequential order. Namely, you need to speak to power, then take decision (not you, but the whole organization) and then focus and implement. Otherwise, it makes no sense to speak the truth and then stalling in decision making or in the realization of your idea.
Here, I am elaborating a little bit more (while keeping the article short) for how these three key aspects are distributed in time and space. &lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="to-succeed-you-need-to-speak-truth-to-power-take-decisions-and-focus">To succeed you need to speak truth to power, take decisions and focus&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="speaking-the-truth-to-power--or-better-discussing-your-view-of-truth-to-power">Speaking the truth to power- Or better discussing your view of truth to power&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Speaking the truth to power seems to be one of the most discussed topics in the business world. According to various factors like personalities, cultures and organization structure, the ease of speaking truth to power might seem not feasible or too risky at all. In a well structured organization with a culture based on transparency, without bureaucracy and empowered teams I do not see why speaking the truth to power is an issue at all, as the “power” is engaged and the teams have the power to affect the operation and decisions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In order to speak the truth to power, you need to have a clear goal and being able to build a fence around your idea. This includes explaining the topic, why it has to be done now and what are the expected outcomes of your proposal. However, the challenge does not stop there. When speaking the truth to power is like leading without authority so you need to empathize and consider any concerns. In general putting your self in the other’s shoes will help you achieve that and also be prepared to listen. While speaking the truth to power is considered as a chance for proposing your ideas it is also a good opportunity to hear from the power. So be prepared to listen and try to use open ended questions to trigger more thoughts and the “slow-thinking” mode. For example, you can ask, “what would it take us to do this in order to achieve that”, or “do you think that we put in risk this if we do that”. That said, you need to be open to listen. In some cases you might even hear a better plan that the one that you had in mind.
&lt;br>
Speaking the truth to power consumes valuable time and attention from key persons in an organization. If you decide to do that you should also consider doing that with parsimony. Also, kindness is mandatory as when mixed with empathy will help others better understand what you are saying. Keep also in mind that in case of disagreement, arrogance or impact has a catastrophic effect. People will forget what you said, but they will never forget how you made them feel, so next time they will be more reluctant to listen to you.
&lt;br>
Here are some take-home messages for speaking the truth:
&lt;br>
Why is needed: Because you assume that your idea should be listened and adapted and you do not have the chance to do that without needing to “speak to the power”.
What do you expect (mechanical adoption): Everyone to hear you, change their minds, accept your positions and start planning
What should happen (productive): Everyone should hear you, argue and try to figure out the why’s. Discuss, learn more, notice a change in both sides and start aggreging on an action plan that will set the basis for change.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="on-taking-decisions">On taking decisions&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Now that you have spoken the truth you need to take some decisions. These decisions will include/describe the when, the what and by whom some actions will take place. Therefore, it is of vital importance to come with a plan describing the goal, the objectives and key results and persons involved. This plan might need to be discussed with subject matter experts and/or modified before put in execution. However, what is important here is to move from saying to doing. Sometimes, it is harder to implement a change as compared to convincing someone that it’s worth it.
&lt;br>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While the plan will summarize the execution of your idea, your decisions need to be clear and sharp. But before that you need to make sure that you are not building a decision zombie tree within your organization. This can happen if a) you procrastinate to take some key decisions, b) have difficulties in drafting the plan or c) you don’t have the resources, capacity or knowledge how to do that.
&lt;br>
Now, that you have drafted you plan, (usually) you once again have no authority in the execution, so you have to lead without authority or even step back and delegate things to other people. In any case, you need to take responsibility in an end-to-end manner and stand by anyone needs you throughout the execution. That said, you always remain accountable for what is happening and your responsibility against your colleagues grows more and more. Last but not least you need to lead by paradigm by being supportive in the change.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="on-remaining-focused">On remaining focused&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>As mentioned previously, you are always accountable for any decisions, actions and outcomes. That means that your journey starts with the pitch of the idea and end with the presentation of the outcomes. Depending on the project management approach, you might also be asked to provide some progress reports, metrics and KPIs depicting the progress.
To cope with all the aforementioned, you need to remain focus and show trust in your plan and the team. Otherwise, you might be faced with scope creep, important delays, difficulties in the adoption of your plan and likely a failed project.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some people are enthralled by the new idea, make some quick decisions and then they delegate everything including the accountability. So remember that enthusiasm is nice for self motivation but useless in realization of the idea. So, to make sure that you don’t fall in this trap, make sure that you have a north star. This should be visible to anyone involved and highlighted across the team often. Also, now that your idea is accepted and executed, it is a good opportunity for you to learn more. You are advised to collect data like what did work and what didn’t and what were the outcomes of each action.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I presented a chain of events needed to succeed as organization, project or business. This includes the ability to communicate with the “power”, taking decisions and remain focus on execution. Next you will find some extra guidelines that summarize my previous paragraphs.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Be prepared to discuss with power. Speaking to power is more like expecting others to blindly accept your positions/proposals. If that happens you should be more worried as compared to be rejected.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Be kind and ask open questions.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Avoid building decision zombies- namely decisions that never spoken to power or never transformed to decisions or abandoned later during execution&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Always remember that you are doing this because you find meaning in that. Supporting change and speaking to power takes a lot of effort, time and large attention spans so it probably worth it&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Hope this helps,&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dimitris Kastaniotis, PhD&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>